<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Articles | William DeMeo]]></title>
  <link href="http://williamdemeo.github.io/blog/categories/articles/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://williamdemeo.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-14T02:29:15-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://williamdemeo.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[William DeMeo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[If it walks like a duck...]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamdemeo.github.io/blog/2014/02/13/if-it-walks-like-a-duck/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-13T21:21:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamdemeo.github.io/blog/2014/02/13/if-it-walks-like-a-duck</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Consider two finite algebras that are the same
except for a relabelling of the operations.
Our intuition tells us that these are simply different names for the same
mathematical structure.
According to the standard definitions, however, not only are such algebras
distinct mathematical objects, but also they are not even isomorphic!</p>

<p><em>Isotopy</em> is another well known notion of “sameness” that is 
broader than isomorphism. However, in a recent paper I proved 
that isotopy is not a notion of algebraic equivalence. 
<!-- more --></p>

<p>$\def\bA{\bf A} \def\bB{\bf B}$
Here is an example of two algebraic structures that are obviously the same
except for a relabelling of the operations: let $\bA$ be an
algebra of size 4 and label the elements of the universe ${1,2,3,4}$.
Suppose $\bA$ has two unary operations, which we label $f^\bA$ 
and $g^\bA$, and suppose 
$f^\bA$ is the permutation $(1,2)(3,4)$ and 
$g^\bA$ is the permutation $(1,3)(2,4)$.</p>

<p>Now let $\mathbf{B}$ be defined in almost the same way except we let
$f^\bB$ be the permutation $(1,3)(2,4)$ and let
$g^\bA$ be the permutation $(1,2)(3,4)$.</p>

<p>Clearly we have simply swapped the names of the operations, and any sane person
would agree that we have two “equivalent” algebraic structures. But these are
not considered equivalent, and they are not even isomorphic according to the
classical definition.</p>

<p>(Insert brief paragraph about isotopy here.)</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/williamdemeo/Isotopy">Isotopy GitHub repository</a>
contains an article in which I present algebras that are isotopic and yet
have vastly different congruence lattices.</p>

<p>Congruence relations of algebras are the kernels of homomorphisms, and the 
congruence lattice is a basic “algebraic” feature of an algebra. Certainly we
cannot accept a notion of “sameness” that equates two algebras with different
congruence lattices.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IEProps]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamdemeo.github.io/blog/2014/02/13/ieprops/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-13T08:42:42-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamdemeo.github.io/blog/2014/02/13/ieprops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://github.com/williamdemeo/IEProps">IEPost GitHub repository</a> contains a draft of the article
<a href="https://github.com/williamdemeo/IEProps/blob/master/CommAlg/DeMeo-IEProps-rev1.pdf">Interval enforceable properties of finite groups</a>, to appear in <em>Communications in Algebra</em>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The paper has been accepted and is in the final review stage. It should appear in print sometime in 2014.
The original submission is available in the file <a href="https://github.com/williamdemeo/IEProps/blob/master/CommAlg/DeMeo-IEProps-rev1.pdf">DeMeo-IEProps-rev1.pdf</a>. The latest revision is in the tex directory.</p>

<p>For questions, comments, or suggestions please <a href="https://github.com/williamdemeo/IEProps/issues">submit an issue</a>.</p>

<p>Thanks for your interest in this work!</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/williamdemeo">@williamdemeo</a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
